Guide to the First Wesleyan Methodist Church of Seneca Falls records,1843-1911.
First Wesleyan Methodist Church of Seneca Falls records,1843-1911
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
First Wesleyan Methodist Church of Seneca Falls records, 1843-1911.
6049
First Wesleyan Methodist Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.)
1 reel microfilm.
Microfilm
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Seven numbered volumes containing trustee meeting minutes (1843-1871, 1880-1913), proceedings of the church's monthly business meetings (1858- 1870), clerk's records (1874-1880) and several miscellaneous papers including receipts, certificates of dismission, and a subscription list. The records document the church's 1869 split, church discipline, finances, and reactions to the Women's Temperance Union and freemasonry.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
On March 27, 1843 a portion of the congregation of the Methodist Episcopal Church of Seneca Falls seceeded and organized the First Wesleyan Society of Seneca Falls at the school house. They built a church costing $1770 on a lot costing $600 at the corner of Hynderse and Fall Streets. That same year, many congregationalists who had joined the Presbyterian Church after their church had disbanded, withdrew over the question of American slavery and joined the Wesleyan church. In 1852 an effort was made to revive the Congregational church, and Rev. B.F. Bradford, who had served the Wesleyan church for 3 years was called to the pastorate. For a year and a half the group worshipped in the concert Hall, but Mr. Bradford's health was impaired, and the group disbanded. Most of the group returned to the Wesleyan congregation where they remained until 1869 when Rev. Lyle, the minister, left the Wesleyans after being foiled in an attempt to transform that church into a Congregational church. Mr. and Mrs. Jabez Matthews and Abram Failing were prominent members who went back and forth between the two groups. The Congregational group called themselves the First Congregational Church of Seneca Falls, and met in the Good Templar's Hall in December 1869 with 63 members.
The split left the Wesleyans with only 60 members down from a high of 200 in 1862, but by 1875 the church was strong enough to dedicate a new church, valued at $14,500. The Sunday School was active, and the church possessed a library of 550 volumes.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Records of the Wesleyan Methodist Church consist of 7 numbered volumes containing trustee meeting minutes (book 1, 1843-71? book 5, 1880-1913); proceedings of the church's monthly business meetings, (book 2, 1858-1863, book 3, 1863-1870); and "clerk's records," 1874-1880 which are probably minutes of monthly business meetings (book 73 1874-80); and several miscellaneous papers including receipts, certificates of dismission and a subscription list. The records document the 1869 split, church discipline and finances, and reactions to the Women's Temperance Union and freemasonry. Records of the Congregational offshoots, though later expurged from the records are legible.
SUBJECTS
Names:
First Wesleyan Methodist Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.); First Congregational Church of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.); First Wesleyan Society of Seneca Falls (Seneca Falls, N.Y.); Woman's Christian Temperance Union.
Subjects:
Church records and registers--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Temperance and religion--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Church discipline.; Methodist church buildings.; Methodist Church--New York (State)--Seneca Falls.; Freemasonry--Religious aspects--Methodists.
Places:
Seneca County (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.; Seneca Falls (N.Y.)--Religious life and customs.
Form and Genre Terms:
Minutes.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Book no. 1, Trustees Record Book March, 1843-1871, Item 1
  - Page 1
    statement on formation, call to build a church, election of trustees
  - Page 2
    subscription list
  - Page 3, July 1844
    trustee's minutes commence. Resolution that the chapel shall not be opened for speaking on political parties
  - Page 4, Feb 1844
    resolution that if the chapel is sold those who contributed toward it must be reimbursed
  - March 1845
    3 recended
  - March 1849
    resolved to insure the chapel, to build a sidewalk and culvert over ditches at the front of the lot
  - April 1855
    voted to charge $5.00 to open the house of worship for mass meetings
  - May 1855
    illegible
  - Apr. 15, 1869
    The president and secretary are directed to take legal proceedings against all or some persons who forcibly entered the church.
  - June 10, 1869
    request by Bro. Denning to use the church for a Quarterly meeting of those "claiming to be of the Wesleyan Church" denied
  - Sept. 10, 1869
    resolved to protect the church property by having the church gate locked except during services and the classroom locked on Sunday and to buy furniture
  - Aug, 10, 1869
    special election of 5 trustees in place of 5 who resigned
  - March 28, 1870
    2 trustees elected
  - Jan. 9, 1871
    begin to plan for a new church list of members of the Wesleyan Church (some marked with x's and dated, mostly 1869 printed roll of members notes, 2 trustees minutes, 1871
- Book no.2, Proceedings of Monthly Business Meetings of the Church. May 1858-1863, Item 2
  - Page 1, May 1858
    Proceedings of regular Monthly Meetings commence, resolved to hold only morning and evening services from now on, and to elect 5 stewards
  - Page 11, Sept. 1858
    resolution disapproving of a brother who burned the church's accounts, plans for a "donation visit" are made
  - Page 27, Jan. 1859
    many new members
  - Page 30, Feb. 13, 1859
  - Page 36, March 13, 1859
    many new members, some baptised by immersion, some by sprinkling
  - Page 38, April 3, 1859
  - Page 42, April 17, 1859
  - Page 45, May 24, 1859
  - Page 46, June 1859
    trial for immoral behavior
  - Pages 62-63, Jan. 1860
    charges of immorality brought
  - Page 69
    sisters are elected stewards resolution forbidding the use of the church to unorthodox ministers
  - Page 73
    requested that Sister Wright take charge of the communion service
  - April 1861
    bro. feels that the church and the U.S. Constitution are incompatible and withdraws
  - Feb. 1862
    sister expelled for immorality
- Book no. 3, Regular Monthly Meeting Book, 1863-1870, Item 3
  - Sept. 1863
    charge against a Member for immorality
  - July 1864
    a "festival" (ice cream social is planned, (earned $176.27)
  - Sept. 1865
    resolved to buy an organ to replace the melodian
  - Dec. 1865
    a parsonage is purchased
  - 1866
    many records illegible
  - Oct. 1869
    resolution to form an executive committee to take over membership duties
  - March 1 1869
    the group begins to call itself a society
  - Apr. 1869
    resolution changing the name to the First Congregational Church
  - Dec. 6 1869
    new trustees elected in place of those who had left the church
- Book no. 4, 1869-1874, Item 4
  - Apr. 12, 1869
    resolution calling for the termination of the Pastor's duties to the congregation
  - Apr. 19, 1869
    executive committee dissolved, stewards, treasurer and clerk dismissed, members dropped by the executive committee restored
  - May 17, 1869
    recommended to consult a lawyer regarding the removal of the trustees and obtaining an injunction forbidding the trustees from paying the minister
  - Nov. 1, 1869 - Nov.1, 1870
    in book 3
  - April 1869-July
    in Book 3 expurged
  - March 21, 1870
    minutes continue
  - Aug. 4, 1872
    Bro. involved with the Odd Fellows agrees to leave the organization rather than be expelled
  - May 11, 1874
    discussion on getting a lecturer on Free Masonry (C.A. Blanchar agreed to allow the Women's Temperance Movement to hold prayer meetings in the church. Five delegates appointed to attend the Syracuse meeting of the Christians opposed to Secret Societies Trustee Records commencing Apr. 5, 1871 discuss construction of the church
  - May 4, 1872
    a list of probationers and members
- Book no. 5, Trustees Records, 1880-1913, Item 5
  "Book for Recording the doings of the Board of Trustees of Wesleyan Methodist Church Commencing 1880"
  - May 3, 1860
    Seneca County Christian Association opposed to Secret Societies is granted permission to use the lecture room
  - July 7, 1880
    Permission granted for use of the lecture room for a lecture to ladies on health
  - Apr. 28, 1912
    renters of the parsonage are given notice to leave since they drink beer bills for hardware dated 1907
- Book no.6, Church Register, Item 6
  - Jan. 27, 1887
    first entry
  - Jan. 28, 1887
    resolution on the membership of Mrs. Susie Palmer membership book purchased because of a resolution passed July 6, 1874
  - Pages 2-15
    lists name, received (when, how), dismissed (when, how)
  - Page 16
    baptisms, none listed
  - Pages 17-22
    roll of probationary members
- Book no. 7, "Clerk's Records", May 1874-1880, Item 7
  - May 11, 1874
    Voted to try to get the Saturday morning class to organize
  - Page 1, May 4, 1874
    list of trustees for 1872-77 and stewards
  - Page 6, May 11, 1874
    church to offer a place for the Women's Temperance movement to hold weekly prayer meetings appointment of 5 delegates to attend the National Christian Association opposed to Secret Societies meeting in Syracuse
  - Page 18, Aug. 3, 1874
    members arrange to attend the Rochester Conference Camp Meeting
  - Page 20
    special meeting to devise ways and means of finishing the church
  - Page 45, Dec. 7, l874
    resolved to cease offering space for meetings to the Women's Temperance Movement because it refuses to identify itself as a Christian organization
  - Dec. 5, 1875
    appointment of delegates to the Anti-Secret Societies convention and to take a collection for the state agent
  - Jan. 1, 1876
    discussion of the resolution concerning the word "Christian" in the Women's Temperance Movement
  - Feb. 7, 1876
    2 men are appointed to protect the church from unruly young men and boys
  - Apr. 3, 1876
    resolution commending the pastor for his services is lost
  - June 1876
    Women's Temperance Union Resolution recended, they can meet in the church
  - Sept. 4, 1876
    report of the examining committee dealing with the unity of the church and its members
  - Oct. 2, 1876
    the pastor states his reason for wishing to leave
  - Apr. 23, 1988
    Annual Report to the Conference. Such reports occur every April from now on
  - Nov. 5, 1877
    motion on having an anti-tobacco sermon
  - Apr. 1, 1878
    resolved that the church opposes appropriating money from the Missionary Fund to any church in Farmington, N.Y.
  - July 1, 1878
    plans to have a raspberry festival
  - March 10, 1870
    George P, Seekill wrote to the church about his legal difficulties
  - March 10, 1879
    member dismissed for Unchristian conduct and breaking Ecclesiastical Law
- Miscellaneous papers tipped in the church record books, Item 8
  Contains receipts (1879, 1901), lists of members (1901, 1911), 2 certificates of dismission from Christ Church in Fayette, and a subscription list (1875) for completing construction of the church.